In this lesson, we're going to learn how to extend interfaces and TypeScript.
So extending interfaces allows us to build on existing object structures instead of repeating
ourselves, which is essential for writing clean and scalable code.
This feature is used heavily in frameworks, libraries, and large code bases.
Let's start with a common problem.
We often have objects that share some properties, but also have their own unique fields.
With its extension, we'd have to repeat the same properties over and over.
So let's zoom in space like this and do interface, we've seen this before.
I'll be user, the ID of number, and name of string.
So this interface defines the basic structure of our user object.
Now let's create a more specific type of user.
We do that by adding interface.
Let's say admin user, and we use the keyword extends, extends, and then the type.
So extends our user type.
And then we specify the property that we want to append, add onto this user object.
Let's say we want to have a role object, a role property, we can set it to admin.
So this extends keywords, allows our admin user to inherit all the properties from user,
and it also adds its own.
Okay, so that means we can create an object like this.
We could do a const, admin user, we can specify it as our admin user,
and then we specify our ID property, our name, let's say Alice,
and then we have this extra property of role, which can then set to admin,
or the live value.
This object must satisfy both the user and the admin user interfaces when they're combined.
Now an interface can extend multiple interfaces.
So we have our user here, now let's just remove this code for moments,
and we're going to define another interface.
This is has permissions.
Let's give it the permissions property.
This is going to be an array of strings.
Now we're going to have another interface.
This is going to be a super admin interface, super admin, which extends both the user,
interface, and also the has permissions interface, both these together.
Now we can define the role and say role is super admin.
Let's let's us to combine multiple behaviors of two interfaces into one single interface.
Let's now have a look at a real-world example that you often see in APIs.
We're going to define an interface, or say base response.
This is going to have a status of number.
And now let's define another interface, perhaps user response.
This is going to extends our base response.
And on this we're going to now define our data, as an object,
as an ID of number, then perhaps a name of string.
Now this pattern keeps our APIs consistent while allowing different payloads.
Now that we've defined our user response,
we could define other responses for other entities, perhaps, for example customer response or product response.
And because he's now extended base response, all of them are going to inherit the status,
and we're going to have the same shape with our data ID to keep things consistent.